Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. So today's דף daf is officially, it
is דף סמך. daf samech. We are at the bottom of נט
עמוד א. nun tet amud aleph. Maybe we'll even get close to
catching up today, push through and all that. So we pick up
at the very bottom of נט עמוד א nun tet amud aleph
and we have been talking about the debate in a ברייתא braita
quoted in the גמרא Gemara whether
another way of looking at these issues of כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
and also looking at the particular category of בתולה. betulah. So when
we dealt with כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, we saw that רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir defined בתולה betulah completely anatomically. It didn't matter if she
had sex, as long as it was ביאה שלא כדרכה, bi’ah shelo
kedarkah, as long as the hymen had been completely in its pristine
state as it were. So she had to be a... she couldn't
be a בוגרת, bogeres, and others that defined it more in terms
of sex. And now we're dealing with the issue about... no,
I'm sorry, am I on the wrong דף? daf?
Okay, forget
that. We're... today's דף daf is... start again, start again, at least
the audio recording.
Okay, take two, I was too rushed. Alright, today's דף daf is
should be דף סא. daf samech aleph. We pick up at the
bottom of דף סמך, daf samech, thank you, in a context of
these issues of defining בתולה betulah for כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, we
get into this debate of the תנאים Tannaim quoted in the גמרא
Gemara about what the תורה Torah says by a כהן kohen is
מטמא metame לאחותו הבתולה הקרובה אליו אשר לא היתה לאיש. l’achoso habetulah
hakerovah eilav asher lo haysah l’ish. So
what is that definition of בתולה אשר לא היתה לאיש והקרובה אליו?
betulah asher lo haysah l’ish v’hakerovah eilav? And how much, number one,
if she's married without having had sex, and number two, in terms
of the בתולה betulah issue, how much is it about her, you
know,
anatomically being a בתולה, betulah, or how much is it about not
having had sex, where the תורה Torah is more explicit about that
אשר לא היתה לאיש? asher lo haysah l’ish? So yesterday we explored
the position of רבי אליעזר... Rabbi Eliezer... who was it? רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that said that even had
she been married אירוסין, erusin,
it was not נישואין—I'm nisu’in sorry, if it was אירוסין erusin and
not נישואין, nisu’in,
yes—that he is מטמא metame to her. I'm running, I'm getting, I'm
going too fast. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
who said that אירוסין erusin would not be a problem. Okay, and
we explored that based on the
פסוק. pasuk. Now we turn to the position of
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that say אירוסין
erusin alone would be a problem and let's take a look at
that. So the גמרא Gemara picks up at the bottom of סמך
עמוד א. samech amud aleph. גמרא Gemara goes like this. רבי יוסי
ורבי שמעון, Rabbi Yosi v’Rabbi Shimon, last narrow line, מאי טעמא, mai
ta’ama, what's their reasoning that say, they say that לאחותו הבתולה, l’achoso
habetulah, it's... אירוסין erusin is no longer... he's no longer מטמא metame
to her? So דרשי הכי, darshei hachi, לאחותו הבתולה, l’achoso habetulah, פרט
לאנוסה ומפותה ומוכת עץ. prat l’anusa u’meputah u’mukat eitz. It's
virgin meaning A, no, not having had sex—אנוסה anusa or מפותה, meputah,
whatever the context would be, rape, seduction—never having had sex; ומוכת עץ
u’mukat eitz and also B, the hymen is complete, not a מוכת
עץ. mukat eitz. אשר לא היתה לאיש, asher lo haysah l’ish, so
that already excludes sex and demands that the hymen is complete, you
know, anatomically. What אשר לא היתה לאיש? asher lo haysah l’ish? פרט
לארוסה. prat l’arusa. Ah, לא היתה lo haysah not being read as
not being had by a man in terms of having had sex
but not having had קידושין kiddushin with a man, right? So and
therefore an ארוסה arusa would be excluded. הקרובה, hakerovah, but the one
who is close, seemingly that they're, you know, that somehow read as
being included as opposed to excluded, לרבות ארוסה שנתגרשה. l’rabos arusa shenitgareshah.
So if she was an ארוסה arusa but then she's divorced, now
she's קרובה kerovah that's fine, which would obviously not be the same
as she had had sex and then she would no longer be
a בתולה betulah in the איסורא, issura, okay. But in terms of
ארוסה, arusa, that was only that presently she was היתה לאיש, haysah
l’ish, that could be
reversed. אליו, eilav, לרבות את הבוגרת. l’rabos es habogeres. So אליו eilav
is coming to somehow also be more inclusive that there's more women
he's מטמא metame to. So even a בוגרת, bogeres, which is interesting,
although מוכת עץ mukat eitz not, that's more of a rupture. בוגרת,
bogeres, which is more natural, maybe just a thinning or however it's
understood, back she would still be considered בתולה. betulah. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara is going to analyze. מוכת עץ mukat eitz is
being treated like an אנוסה anusa and a מפותה. meputah. הקרובה לרבות
ארוסה שנתגרשה. hakerovah l’rabos arusa shenitgareshah. גמרא Gemara says, so הקרובה hakerovah
is coming to say that if she now she is divorced, it's
okay because she's still בתולה betulah and לא היתה לאיש lo haysah
l’ish and fine. So the גמרא Gemara says והאמר רבי שמעון ראויה
לכהן גדול מטמא לה שאין ראויה לכהן גדול אין מטמא לה. v’ha’amar
Rabbi Shimon re’uyah l’Kohen Gadol metame lah she’ein re’uyah l’Kohen Gadol ein
metame lah. Wait a minute, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said that we
have to apply the same standard to this issue of a כהן...
kohen... taming to a sister
and the issue about would she be able to marry a כהן
גדול. Kohen Gadol. So if a woman was ארוסה arusa and then
divorced, she wouldn't be able to marry a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
Now of course you could say רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon was only
saying that from the in terms of the definition of the idea
of בתולה. besula. How do we define virgin here? And say we
define virgin here how we define it by כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
But the גמרא Gemara understands that it's a broader statement and says
no, the only woman a כהן Kohen is מטמא mitamei to is
a sister that could marry a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So if
she was ארוסה arusa and then גרושה, gerusha, she couldn't marry a
כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So the גמרא Gemara says because she's a
גרושה. gerusha. So the גמרא Gemara says no, שאני התם דריבה רחמנא.
shani hasam d'rabi rachmana. No because in yeah that is a general
rule but there's a פסוק pasuk overrode it. The פסוק pasuk said
that she would. Okay I think that the better explanation of that
or maybe to interpret what the גמרא Gemara means is is that
his requirements all he's saying is that you use the same definition
of בתולה besula that you get from כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, not
everything is defined by כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Okay so now the
גמרא Gemara says like
this, קרובה. krova. שאני התם דריבה רחמנא קרובה. shani hasam d'rabi rachmana
krova. קרובה krova comes to include, therefore includes her after she's divorced.
אי הכי מוכת עץ נמי? iy hachi mukas etz nami?
So why don't we say that by a מוכת עץ mukas etz
let's say that
ריבה rabi so let's include that because if we're including more of
the marginal cases and saying that that's okay. The גמרא Gemara says
no, קרובה אחת ולא שתים, krova achas v'lo shtayim, it only says
קרובה krova once so it can only include one woman. ומאי חזית?
u'mar isa? All right ומאי חזית u'mar isa why do you more
include this woman who is divorced as opposed to מוכת עץ? mukas
etz? האי איתעביד בה מעשה והאי לא איתעביד בה מעשה. hai isavi
ba ma'aseh v'hai lo isavi ba ma'aseh. In one case nothing physical
has happened or in the other it has, meaning in one case
it's not an aspect about her being a virgin or not. So
therefore he's willing to include the idea that ארוסה arusa is out
of the category
even though it's not because she's not a virgin and so even
though she is a virgin that he's willing to say if she's
no longer an ארוסה arusa we'll put her back and the fact
that she is a גרושה gerusha is not relevant to this discussion.
But the definition of virgin that he is that he's learning from
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and therefore we're not interested in sort of
being more inclusive in terms of that. It's a broader category as
we learn from כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. It becomes a community obligation
to bury her then it's like let's say she's an only daughter
and then a parent? Yeah no family obligation which is kids father
brothers whatever yeah okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, it
could be a מצוה. mitzvah. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like
this, okay so that's that. They basically say that if she's an
ארוסה arusa no but if she's נתגרשה nisgarsha yes. Okay now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, רבי יוסי מדשבקיה לבר זוגיה מכלל דמוכת
עץ רבי מאיר שרי ליה. Rabbi Yose mid'shavkei l'bar zugei miklal d'mukas
etz Rabbi Meir sharei lei. So if you remember the ברייתא brayta
from yesterday the גמרא Gemara started by saying you have רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that say an ארוסה arusa
he can be מטמא mitamei to her. You had רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said he cannot be מטמא mitamei
to her. And then it says how about a מוכת עץ? mukas
etz? So it says you can be מטמא mitamei to her. I'm
sorry מוכת עץ mukas etz you cannot be מטמא mitamei to her
says רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon because רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would apply
the same standard as by a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So we
had רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon saying ארוסה
arusa cannot be מטמא mitamei her. Then it said when it came
to מוכת עץ mukas etz it said רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said
you can't be מטמא mitamei her. What happened to רבי יוסי? Rabbi
Yose? Where did he go? So clearly he would disagree. He would
say מוכת עץ mukas etz can be מטמא mitamei to her. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this, רבי יוסי מדשבקיה לבר זוגיה Rabbi
Yose mid'shavkei l'bar zugei
since רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose left his companion there right he abandoned
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon when it came to when he was with
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon when you said not an ארוסה arusa but
when רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon was saying not a מוכת עץ mukas
etz he was nowhere to be seen. So since he abandoned רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon מכלל דמוכת עץ רבי מאיר שרי ליה, miklal d'mukas
etz Rabbi Meir sharei lei, he must hold like מוכת עץ mukas
etz like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says that it's not a
problem. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says מנא ליה minalei where does
he get it from? מלא הייתה לאיש. mi lo hayesa le'ish. Because
it says לא הייתה לאיש lo hayesa le'ish it defines it. What
does virgin mean in this context? In this context virgin means not
having had sex, it's not anatomical. So the גמרא Gemara says והא
אפיקתיה, v'ha asiktei, one minute but you can't do that because רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose also says that ארוסה arusa is no good and
because he learned הייתה לאיש hayesa le'ish not about sex but about
being married. So if לא הייתה לאיש lo hayesa le'ish is saying
never married how could he also say that that defines that virgin
is only about sex? So the גמרא Gemara says no, חד מלא
היתה וחד לאיש. chad mi'lo hayesa v'chad l'ish. No לא היתה lo
hayesa means never married so that's why he excludes ארוסה. arusa. לאיש
l'ish means that when we're talking about sex we're talking about when
we're talking about virgin we're talking about having had sex, we're not
talking about having been with a man, we're not talking about מוכת
עץ. mukas etz. Okay, by the way it's worth noting that רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, the same רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that defined בתולה
besula completely anatomically by כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and said even a
מוכת עץ mukas etz is a problem, even a בוגרת bogeres is
a problem, but ביאה שלא כדרכה bi'ah she'lo k'darkah is not, here
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is doing a complete reversal and saying that
basically מוכת עץ mukas etz no problem. The only problem is לא
הייתה לאיש lo hayesa le'ish whether she had had sex or not.
So it's quite fascinating that he says yeah there are two definitions
of virgin out there, the anatomical one and never having had sex.
The anatomical one we're going to say that's by כהן גדול. Kohen
Gadol. Never having had sex... Okay, so now the Gemara says like
this. אלאו לרבות הבוגרת. Alav lerabos habogeret. So now it says אלאו
Alav that even if מוכת עץ mukat etz not בוגרת bogeret yet,
somehow אלאו Alav is coming to say he is מטמא metamei to
a sister who is a בוגרת. bogeret. So the Gemara says דאמר
רבי שמעון בתולה בתולה שלמה משמע. de'amar Rabi Shimon: Besulah, besulah shleima
mashma. We said a day or two ago that when he was
looking at the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol פסוק, pasuk, בתולה besulah meant
complete בתולים. besulim. So here it says אחותו הבתולה, achoso habesulah, so
why doesn't we have say complete בתולים besulim and excluding a בוגרת?
bogeret? So he answers obvious which we have a פסוק pasuk that
tells you otherwise. So the Gemara says טעמי דידיה נמי התם מהכא.
taamei didey nami hasam mehacha. Yes, his reason over there to learn
out that בתולה besulah normally means complete complete and even before being
a maturity is because of what he figures out from these פסוקים.
pesukim. Why? מהכא דדריש הכי. mehacha, dedarish hachi. This is how he
learns the פסוקים. pesukim. מאלאו לרבות הבוגרת. mi-alav lerabos habogeret. Since the
תורה Torah told me already אלאו Alav to say that a כהן
Kohen is מטמא metamei to a sister who is a בוגרת, bogeret,
even though it already said the word בתולה, besulah, מכלל, michlal, why
did I need אלאו Alav to include a בוגרת? bogeret? From this
I can infer דבתולה de-besulah that the word בתולה besulah itself, בתולה
שלמה משמע, besulah shleima mashma, would have implied a perfect בתולים besulim
even before puberty. So the fact the תורה Torah had to say
אלאו Alav to tell me בוגרת bogeret means that by the word
בתולה besulah I would have excluded בוגרת bogeret and from here I
learn the principle that the word בתולה besulah by itself means not
a בוגרת, bogeret, a complete even before the even before any puberty
and any change in the בתולים. besulim. Fine. Anyway, those are the
various debates. What's interesting is number one, the idea that a sister,
even if she's just an ארוסה arusa and never and it's not
about sex, might be that not מטמא. metamei. And B, different possible
definitions. רבי שמעון Rabi Shimon says you use the same definition by
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, but for רבי מאיר Rabi Meir it's a
complete reversal. By כהן גדול Kohen Gadol it's all anatomical, here it's
all about sex. Okay, now the Gemara continues like this: תניא רבי
שמעון בן יוחי אומר. tanya, Rabi Shimon ben Yochai omer. How do
we get to רבי שמעון בן יוחי Rabi Shimon ben Yochai and
now we get to a very different discussion and an extremely relevant
one, not about כהן גדול Kohen Gadol anymore. תניא רבי שמעון בן
יוחי אומר גיורת פחותה מבת שלוש שנים ויום אחד כשרה לכהונה. tanya,
Rabi Shimon ben Yochai omer: Giyores pahusa mibat shalosh shanim veyom echad
kesheira lekehunah. So a woman who converted less than three years old,
a girl, meaning that she converted because her mother converted her or
whatever an adult converted her, she can marry a כהן. Kohen. Now
assuming of course that a גיורת סתם giyores stam cannot marry a
כהן. Kohen. We haven't established that yet but if you peek ahead
at ס"א ע"א, Samech Aleph Amud Aleph, let's take a look and
it says over there, where is it? Hold on. Yeah, look at
the last משנה Mishnah on ס"א ע"א. Samech Aleph Amud Aleph. כהן
הדיוט לא ישא אילונית אלא אם כן יש לו אשה ובנים רבי
יהודה אומר אף על פי שיש לו אשה ובנים, Kohen hedyot lo
yisa ilonis ela im ken yesh lo isha ubanim, Rabi Yehuda omer
af pi sheyesh lo isha ubanim, ignoring that for now, לא ישא
אילונית. lo yisa ilonis. So רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda says even if
he's פסול pasul for פרו ורבו pru u'revu he can't marry a
woman who can't have kids, שהיא זונה האמורה בתורה. she-hi zona ha'amura
batorah. וחכמים אומרים אין זונה אלא גיורת ומשוחררת ושנבעלה בעילת זנות. vachachamim
omrim: Ein zona ela giyores umshuchreres sheniv'ala bevias znus. א זונה's A
zona only a woman who converted or was a slave that was
freed or has had forbidden sex. What type of forbidden sex, whatever.
We'll discuss that but what I wanted you to see is the
basic הלכה halacha that a גיורת giyores is being put in the
category of זונה, zona, presumably because of an assumption that a non-Jewish
woman is a woman who has sex, isn't guided by sexual mores.
That's the assumption. Now you could think about this in one of
two ways and this is a big מחלוקת ראשונים ותוספות. machlokes Rishonim
ve'Tosfos. Either you could say essentially because we're חושד choshed that she
had sex with a non-Jew. We suspect that that's what happened. And
sex with a non-Jew, like if a single woman has sex with
a Jew, a Jewish woman has sex with a Jew, other than
רבי אליעזר פנוי הבא על פנויה, Rabi Eliezer: panui ha'ba al pnuya,
we say that doesn't invalidate her for כהן. Kohen. It's not like
a איסור כרת issur kareis or whatever. But if a single woman
has sex with a Jew, a Jewish woman has sex with a
non-Jew, excuse me, it does invalidate her for כהן Kohen because there's
no קידושין תופסין kiddushin tosin by a non-Jew. And since marriage is
impossible with a non-Jew, then that act basically is defined as more
fundamentally as a ביאת זנות. be'as znus. Wait, but a non-Jew had
sex with a non-Jew before she converted? So why should that be
a problem? Or what if they did it legally as a marriage?
Okay, but one way of starting this issue about a גיורת giyores
is to say no, sex with a non-Jew even if it was
a non-Jew having that sex with a non-Jew would make her זונה.
zona. And since we suspect that non-Jews aren't being guided by sexual
mores, any woman who converts we're concerned that she's had sex with
a non-Jew and that's why she's in the category of זונה. zona.
So if that's the way of thinking about it, it's basically a
type of a ספק זונה, safek zona, maybe she had sex. But
anyway, it's because of what might have happened, whether, however much confidence
we feel it did, it did happen. The other way of saying
it might be, no, maybe, you know, because she had a non-Jewish
identity, again, with the assumption that non-Jews aren't guided by similar sexual
mores, so that makes her from part of the, you know, sort
of a liberal, uninhibited west, and therefore that labels her as זונה,
Zonah, whatever activity she had. You understand? So it's not whether having
had that, maybe she had that act and that would have made
her a זונה. Zonah. She's a זונה Zonah because she was a
non-Jew, so she was in the category of libertines, okay? And whether
she actually did something about it or not, that labels her, okay?
Very different way of thinking about it. Normally the general assumption is
the first way, but it's not so black and white. So it's
interesting to think about, well, let's say people want to argue, let's
say you can know בודאי, bevada'i, and you know, do you treat
the whole thing as a ספק דאורייתא safek d'Oraita or as a
real דאורייתא? d'Oraita? Whatever, there are different, anyway these are, these are
the types of questions. So, wait, are we really positing that at
some point, either in the time of חז"ל Chazal or in the
time of תורה, Torah, that all non-Jewish societies were, you know, were
sexually... No, but, yeah, but you know, but we're positing that that
might be the legal category that חז"ל Chazal put them in. You
know, that might be a, the perspective that חז"ל Chazal had. You
know, sort of like, sort of like in recent פרשיות, parshiyot, you
know, it's like אברהם Avraham goes to מצרים, Mitzrayim, right? And it's
like, you know, he says, "Oh, אין יראת אלוהים, ein yirat Elohim,
etc.," right? And then whatever, and then by אבימלך, Avimelech, and then
you have the same thing by יצחק. Yitzchak. It's like he seems
to have made the same assumption, but it seems like they were
much better over there with אבימלך Avimelech and the פלשתים Plishtim than
they were in מצרים. Mitzrayim. But you know, but I'm like, not
all non-Jews are like this way, you know, doesn't sort of, don't
assess case by case. I'm learning with some of the guys on
כולל, kollel, right? מסכת עבודה זרה, Masechet Avodah Zarah, right? And how
much do we make sort of like broad character characterizations or not?
So I'm not, so I would say two things. I would say
a, that might have, that certainly, you know, it certainly might have
been their perspective. And b, even if they were aware of differences,
they might have felt that was like the legal category to put
it in. You know, like the idea is, is like someone once
said the most, like for better or worse, like one of the
most amazing things that the Jews have managed like to convince the
whole world of, is that the way you categorize people is Jews
and non-Jews. Like, you know, what? You know, Jews and Greeks and
Persians and Mongols. No, no, no, fundamentally there's Jews and there are
non-Jews. So if you look at the non-Jews as a fundamentally undifferentiated
rest of the world and you see in general that their looser
sexual mores, you just give it one הלכתית halachic category. But that
would be my guess. Yeah, in רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon's time in
the Roman society he lived in, the characteristic, the idea that non-Jews
were sexually licentious was certainly true for that time and that community.
Right, so and that would have, could have led to a general
characterization. Okay, so let's move back. So the assumption is that this
גיורת giyoret is normally a זונה, Zonah, but what if she converts
less than three years and a day? And less than three years
and a day, now it's funny. If the question was, do we
actually think she's had sexual activity? Probably even three years and a
day we don't think it. But if, whether it is הלכתית halachically
considered an act of sex, so less than three years and a
day, maybe again, under the assumption that the hymen would grow back
or whatever reason it is, חז"ל Chazal understood that that would not,
even if sex occurred, would not הלכתית halachically be defined as an
act of sex. If she were a Jew. So, right, so, so
what happens if she converts less than three years and a day?
If she's had to be, really even be a גיורת, giyoret, she's
not a בת דעת. bat da'at. No, no, no, so an adult
converted her. That's a separate סוגיה sugya about an adult converting a
minor. Okay, so let's take a look. Her parents converted with her
or other cases. תניא, Tanya, רבי שמעון בר יוחאי אומר: Rabbi Shimon
bar Yochai omer: גיורת פחותה מבת שלוש שנים ויום אחד, Giyoret p’chuta
mibat shalosh shanim v’yom echad, פחות משלוש שנים ויום אחד, pachot mishalosh
shanim v’yom echad, כשירה לכהונה, kshera l’khuna, שנאמר וכל הטף בנשים אשר
לא ידעו משכב זכר החיו לכם. shene’emar v’chol hataf banashim asher lo
yadu mishkav zachar hachayu lachem. This is by מדין, Midyan, all of
the infants, whatever it was, or the children that have never had
sex, you can keep them alive. Okay, and how do we know
that means even for כהנים? kohanim? שהרי פנחס עמהם, sheharei Pinchas imahem,
because פנחס Pinchas was there and he's a כהן, kohen, so החיו
לכם. hachayu lachem. So therefore you see that you can have somebody
that was started non-Jewish and is מותר mutar to a כהן. kohen.
ורבנן, V’rabbanan, and he's going to assume they're less than three years
and that's the idea of טף. taf. ורבנן, V’rabbanan, the rabbis would
say that, לעבדים ולשפחות, la’avadim ul’shfachot, we're not talking for wives, you
can have them for slaves. So the גמרא Gemara says if that's
true, of course then why would it matter if they'd had sex
or not, but that could be because, you know, because the women
were cause בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael to sin, or whatever, so it's
not about having them as wives. אי הכי בת שלוש שנים ויום
אחד נמי. Ei hachi bat shalosh shanim v’yom echad nami. So if,
says the גמרא, Gemara, okay, we get how he's reading the פסוק,
pasuk, but if it's about not having had sex, and it's אשר
לא ידעו משכב זכר, asher lo yadu mishkav zachar, so why not
say even three years and a day if they didn't have sex
it would be okay? No, כדי רב הונא, k’di Rav Huna, that's
because of רב הונא. Rav Huna. דרב הונא רמי, D’Rav Huna rami,
רב הונא Rav Huna showed a contradiction. כתיב, Ktiv, one פסוק... pasuk...
So הא אינה יודעת *ha eino yoda'at* if it's a woman who's
not had sex קימו *kimo* so you can keep her. מכלל דאתא
בין ידעו בין לא ידעו קיימי *mikhlal d'ata bein yadu bein lo
yadu kaimi*. So it's clearly not about being an adult woman or
a minor, it's about having had sex. But if we're going to
read it like this way it says an adult woman and she
hasn't had sex and then if she's had sex it's a problem,
not sex is fine. So that would suggest that if there's then
going to be a difference in terms of a minor, that a
minor even having had sex wouldn't be a problem. ובין ידעו ובין
לא ידעו קיימי *v'bein yadu u'vein lo yadu kaimi* wouldn't be a
problem. וכתיב *u'kh'tiv* but the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says וכל הטף בנשים
אשר לא ידעו משכב זכר החיו לכם *v'khol hataf banashim asher lo
yadu mishkav zachar hachayu lakhem*. If it's a minor who hasn't had
sex. הידעי *ha'yada'ei* if it's minor who's had sex הרוגו *harogu* kill
her. So meaning basically what it's saying is that there are two
criteria going on in these פסוקים psukim *psukim*. One is having had
sex or not, and the other is adult or minor, אשה isha,
*isha* or טף *taf*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like make
up your mind, which is it about? What what's the dividing line?
Is it אשה isha. *isha* versus טף *taf* or is it ידעו
*yadu* and לא ידעו *lo yadu*? What's the distinction? So one minute,
so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says let's read the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
I know what you could say, let's read the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says הא בראויה להיבעל הכתוב מדבר *ha
b're'uya l'hibba'el hakatuv medabber*. Ah, so the difference is in a way
between a woman and a minor. But the reason the difference of
a woman and a minor is because having had sex, it's not
the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* doesn't mean have they had sex or not,
it means could they have had sex? So if it's an אשה
isha, *isha*, a woman, and she could have had sex, אשר *asher*...
so so then not a problem. If it's however a minor since
she's אשר לא ידעו משכב זכר *asher lo yadu mishkav zachar* since
they couldn't have had sex because we're under three years old, therefore
it's not a problem. Okay, so he's resolving the fact that there
are two different criteria that are going on and there's an excluded
middle there, right? And he basically says no, the idea of ידעו
*yadu* and לא ידעו *lo yadu* doesn't mean in fact whether they've
had sex, it means whether they could have had sex. And that's
why fundamentally it's a difference of an adult or a minor, except
a real minor under three years old. Okay, so that's how he's
reading it and therefore from there he learns that there's an איסור
*issur* that it's מותר *mutar* to a כהן kohen *kohen* if she's
a convert under three years old. תניא Tanya, נמי הכי *Tanya nami
hakhi*, we taught similarly, וכל אשה יודעת איש בראויה להיבעל הכתוב מדבר
*v'khol isha yoda'at ish b're'uya l'hibba'el hakatuv medabber*. So it doesn't mean
having had sex, it means having been able to have had sex.
אתה אומר בראויה להיבעל או אינו אלא בניבעלה ממש *ata omer b're'uya
l'hibba'el o eino ela b'nivala mamash*? Do you mean she's fit to
have sex or does it mean she actually had sex? כשהוא אומר
וכל הטף בנשים אשר לא ידעו משכב זכר *k'shehu omer v'khol hataf
banashim asher lo yadu mishkav zachar*, there it says infants who haven't
known, so why is it saying infants? So הא בראויה להיבעל הכתוב
מדבר *ha b're'uya l'hibba'el hakatuv medabber*, we're talking about whether it's fit
for having had sex not whether in practice they have. Now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says מנא ידעי Mina yad'ei? *mena yadei*? Okay, how
do you know? So how did they know at that time, right?
If she's said... now you could say well how old is she?
Not whether she's had sex. But I don't understand, you capture all
these women and you have babies, how do you determine whether they're
three years and a day or two years and and 11 months?
And how do you know how old they are? The same way
you could ask how do you know if she's had sex, right?
How do you know? So אמר רב הונא Rav Huna בר ביזנא
אמר רבי amar Rabi שמעון חסידא *Amar Rav Huna bar Bizna amar
Rabbi Shimon Chasida*, העבירום לפני הציץ *he'evirum lifnei ha'tzitz*. They passed them
before the ציץ Tzitz. *tzitz*, right? The... on the כהן גדול kohen
gadol. *kohen gadol*. Back to כהן גדול kohen gadol *kohen gadol*. כל
שפניה מוריקות *kol shepaneha morikot*, any woman whose whose face basically you
know turned jaundiced, בידוע שהיא ראויה להיבעל *bi'yadu'a shehi re'uya l'hibba'el*, then
you knew that she was more than three years old. רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* of course says this is a נס *nes*, nobody explains this
naturalistically. וכל שאין פניה מוריקות בידוע שאינה ראויה להיבעל *v'khol she'ein paneha
morikot bi'yadu'a she'eina re'uya l'hibba'el*. Okay, so there was some נס *nes*
there that we figured out which were older than three and which
were not. אמר רב נחמן *Amar Rav Nachman*, סימן לעבירה הדרוקן *siman
la'avera hadrokan*. By the way if you want to know if if
somebody has sinned, it's... if they have like a jaundice. Now בביאה
*b'via*... no, it may mean sex, עבירה *avera* often does mean classically
sex. Although it's interesting, for some reason my mind wasn't going there.
But if you look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, רש"י *Rashi* seems to
more generalize it and describe it in naturalistic terms, the second statement:
פניהם של עוברי עבירה מוריקין *pneihem shel ovrei avera morikin*. Like you
know people sin sometimes you can see it on their face. Okay,
in some way or another. Well it it becomes white, right? In
other words it's empty, it's empty the blood. Right, now תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafot* does say right... תוספות Tosafot. *Tosafot* does say that מוריקות *morikot*
is not the same as הדרוקן *hadrokan*, I think תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*
says that. But what is מוריקות *morikot*? Well... מוריקין וירקין *morikin v'yerakin*
or yellow? Oh no no... no no no, תוספות Tosafot. *Tosafot* says
is the same as הדרוקן *hadrokan*, it's not the same as ירקון
*yerakon* which is jaundice. I know, how how do they explain מוריקות
*morikot* anyway? Bloating? Bloating? No, פניהם מוריקות *pneihem morikot*. And רש"י *Rashi*
there proposed and הערוך *he'Arukh* described הדרוקן *hadrokan* as a disease whose
primary symptom is a bloating of the stomach. Aha, and what do
they say about פניהם מוריקות *pneihem morikot*? And no one identifies it
with dropsy. Or what does Steinzald say? Sallow, to describe her to
be sallow. Sallow. Identifies it with dropsy. He identifies it as ascites,
which is bloating in the abdomen. Oh, same thing. Oh, same thing,
okay. So now it all fits, whatever else they say. Sallow? Sallow
means like pale? What sallow means. Yeah. Basically. Okay, fine. Anyway, something
happens to the stomach. Bloating. Bloating. But that's important. I told staff
that it wasn't jaundice and I was reading this text. Bloating is
like a soak-up in it, right? That's a good point. Ascites, A-S-C-I-T-E-S,
which means what? I'm here. Okay, moving on. Okay, we gotta move
on. Okay. אמר רב נחמן: כיוצא בדבר. Keyotze bedavar. Similarly, about a
miracle in a very similar area of determining what was going on
with the women. וימצאו מיושבי יביש גלעד ארבע מאות נערה בתולה אשר
לא ידעו איש למשכב זכר. Vayimtze'u miyoshvei Yavesh Gilad arba me'ot na'ara
betula asher lo yad'u ish lemishkav zachar. So if people remember this
story, basically after all the tribes sort of ganged up on בנימין
Binyamin and pretty much wiped them out or did wipe them out
almost completely, and then took an oath that they couldn't give their
daughters for them to marry and then they regretted their oath. And
what are you going to do about this whole tribe and where
are they going to get wives? So then they said, "Oh wait,
we got an idea. Was there anybody who wasn't part of the
oath? Oh yeah, there was these יושבי... yoshvei... what is it? יביש
גלעד. Yavesh Gilad. They weren't part of the oath. You know why
they weren't part of the oath? Because they didn't participate in the
battle. What? They didn't participate in the battle? Let's go kill them
out." So they went ahead and they wiped out all the men,
and then they seized the women who hadn't had sex from that
יושבי yoshvei from יביש גלעד, Yavesh Gilad, and then they gave them
over to the tribe of בנימין. Binyamin. Okay. So... it's like this
whole story by the foundational stories by Rome, not even a myth,
right? About the whole thing about, what is it? The rape of
the something women? The Sabine women. Yeah. Okay. Anyway, moving on. So,
okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. מנא ידעי? How
did they know these women of יביש גלעד Yavesh Gilad that they
were now giving over to בנימין, Binyamin, how did they know they
never had sex? אמר רב כהנא: Amar Rav Kahana: הושיבום על פי
חבית של יין. Hoshivum al pi chavit shel yayin. So here we
have a test which didn't need the ציץ. Tzitz They had them
sit on a barrel of wine. Okay, the גמרא Gemara believes that
this was a way of determining. בעולה ריחה נודף. Be'ula reicha nodef.
A woman who's had sex, if she's sitting on top of a
barrel of wine, then a smell emanates from her. ובתולה אין ריחה
נודף. Uvtula ein reicha nodef. But if it's a בתולה, betula, it
doesn't. Maybe the גמרא Gemara thought that the wine, the vapors, go
into her up, you know, up her vaginal canal or something and
the בתולה betula prevents it from going. I don't know what they
thought. Anyway, okay, so this is what they say. So the גמרא
Gemara says, ונעברינהו לפני ציץ. Vena'avreinhu lifnei Tzitz. Well, I don't understand,
there was still a ציץ Tzitz at that time, why don't you
say that's how they determined this? So אמר רב כהנא בריה דרב
נתן: Amar Rav Kahana brei d'Rav Natan: לכם כתיב. Lachem ketiv. The
ציץ Tzitz is supposed to be something that finds לרצון. leratzon. לרצון
ולא לפורענות. Leratzon velo lepur'anut. It's for רצון ratzon and not for
פורענות. pur'anut. So here it was you wiped out a whole tribe.
Oh man. Maybe you get to that. Maybe if the women that
weren't virgins, maybe they would have killed here from יושבי גלעד. yoshvei
Gilad. It's not a good thing going on here. So גמרא Gemara
says, אי הכי במנין נמי. Ei hachi beminyan nami. So there also
there you're really the ones that are going to fail the test
you're going to kill. So אמר רב אשי: Amar Rav Ashi: להם
כתיב. Lahem ketiv. No, for them, for בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael it
has to be לרצון. leratzon. להם לרצון ולא לפורענות. Lahem leratzon velo
lepur'anut. ולעובדי כוכבים אפילו לפורענות. Ule'ovdei kokhavim afilu lepur'anut. But for פורענות
pur'anut the ציץ can even work. Very nice. אמר רב יעקב בר
אידי אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי: Amar Rav Yaakov bar Idi amar
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi: הלכה כרבי שמעון בן יוחי. Halacha k'Rabbi Shimon
ben Yochai. We rule like רבי שמעון בן יוחי Rabbi Shimon ben
Yochai that says that פחותה מבת שלוש שנים pachuta mibat shalosh shanim
is מותרת לכהן. muteret lekohen. Very important, right? Because you definitely have
cases of underage converts, women who convert when they're pregnant or even
women that convert when they're, you know, small children and so on.
So he says we rule like רבי שמעון בן יוחי. Rabbi Shimon
ben Yochai. מותרת לכהן. Muteret lekohen. אמר ליה רב זירא לרב יעקב
בר אידי: Amar lei Rav Zeira leRav Yaakov bar Idi: בפירוש שמיע
לך או מכללא שמיע לך? Beferush shmi'a lach o miklala shmi'a lach?
When you said this in the name of רבי יהושע בן לוי,
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, did you hear him explicitly say it or
did you infer it? מאי כללא? Mai klala? Why might you have
assumed that it was implicit? דאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי: De'amar Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi: עיר אחת הייתה בארץ ישראל שקראו לה עיר. Ir
achat hayita b'Eretz Yisrael shekar'u la Ir. There was a certain city
in Israel that there was a... or town... that there was some
question about somebody's personal status, not about the whole town presumably, about
a certain person, a certain woman's status. ושיגר רבי את רבי רומנוס.
Veshigar Rebbe et Rabbi Romanos. Rebbe sent Rabbi Romanos. ובדקה ומצא בה
בת גיורת. Uvadka u'matza ba bat giyoret. He checked into it and
he found that the problem was that there was a daughter of
a convert, which presumably means that פחותה מבת שלוש שנים... pachuta mibat
shalosh shanim... presumably means that she herself also had converted, was converted
by her mother under three years old. והכשירה רבי לכהונה. Vehichshira Rebbe
lekehuna. Rebbe said don't get so... don't get so worked up. She's
fine. And here it would also mean she can stay married to
a כהן kohen, because the reason everybody was getting up in a
tizzy was she was already married and people were saying it's a
problem. And Rebbe said, "No, it's fine, she can stay." stay married
to a כהן kohen *Kohen*. So that's how I hear that under
three years old is not a problem. So אמר ליה *amar lei*,
so he said back to him, so he said: Did you infer
from that case or did you hear it explicitly? So he said
בפירוש שמיע לי *beferush shemia li*, no, no, I heard him explicitly
rule that way. אי מכללא מאי *ei michlala mai*, so why does
it matter? I mean, okay, maybe he got it—he inferred it. It's
still a good inference. No, cause you can always question certain inferences.
דילמא שאני התם הואיל ואינסב אינסב *dilma shani hatam hoil ve'insiv insiv*,
maybe there he was more lenient because she was already married. Maybe
we wouldn't have allowed it לכתחילה *lechatchila*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
one minute. How do you know that? רב *Rav* and רבי יוחנן
*Rabbi Yochanan* both said yesterday, בוגרת ומוכת עץ לא ישא *bogeres umukat
etz lo yisa*, a כהן גדול kohen gadol. *Kohen Gadol* can't marry
a בוגרת *bogeres* or מוכת עץ *mukat etz*, אם נשא נשא *im
nasa nasa*, but if he marries he can stay married. So here
too, maybe he can stay married, but it's not fundamentally—it's not allowed.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, you can't make that comparison.
הכי השתא *hachi hasha*, what kind of comparison is that? בשלמא התם
סופה להיות בוגרת תחתיו *bishlama hatam sofa lihyot bogeres tachtav*, there in
the end she's going to grow—be become an adult while she's married
and she's going to become a בעולה *beulah* when she's married to
him. So there it might be that we don't, you know, we're
able to tolerate the situation even though maybe he's still doing an
איסור *issur* or maybe the whole problem is rooted in the קידושין
kiddushin *kiddushin* and not in the ניסואין *nisuin* and not in the
ongoing marriage. Okay, cause there the status always changes. But הכא סופה
להיות זונה zonah? תחתיו *hacha sofa lihyot zonah tachtav*? Here for a
גיורת Giyoret, *giyoret* is a זונה zonah. *zonah*, right? And in a
normal situation we would never tolerate a כהן Kohen, *Kohen* married to
a זונה zonah *zonah*. So why are we going to tolerate it
if it's, you know, just because they're already married now? Okay, so
there we tolerate the situation because that winds up happening anyway in
every single normal case of a כהן גדול kohen gadol, *Kohen Gadol*
married to a קטנה ktana *ketana*. Okay, but anyway that winds up
happening anyway. But here we wouldn't tolerate it if it were אסור
assur *assur*. So the fact that it was tolerated clearly shows that
it's מותר *muttar*. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s point is A,
he said it explicitly and B, yes, even if it were just
inferred, it would clearly show that it was מותר *muttar*. No question
there. רב ספרא מתני לה מכללא *Rav Safra masni lah michlala*. Now
רב ספרא *Rav Safra* learned that this was figured out only by
inference, it wasn't told explicitly. דקשיא ליה *dekashya lei*, and he was
bothered—it's not a good inference, they were already married. ומשני ליה הכי
*umashni lei hachi*, and he gave the same answer that we just
gave. No, it is a good inference because even though they were
already married, we wouldn't have tolerated it. Okay, now ההוא כהנא דאינסב
גיורת פחותה מבת שלש שנים ויום אחד *hahu kahana de'insiv giyoret pechuta
mibat shalosh shanim veyom echad*. There was a certain כהן Kohen *Kohen*
who married a גיורת *giyoret* who had converted less than three years
and one day. אמר ליה רב נחמן בר יצחק *amar lei Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak*, now up until now everything is like fine, fine,
fine, fine, fine. Now we reverse. Says רב נחמן בר יצחק *Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak* to him, מאי האי *mai hai*, what are you
doing? אמר ליה דאמר רבי יעקב בר אידי אמר רבי יהושע בן
לוי הלכה halachic כרבי שמעון בן יוחי *amar lei damar Rabbi Yaakov
bar Idi amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi halacha keRabbi Shimon ben Yochai*,
we rule like רבי שמעון בר יוחאי *Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai*. By
the way, in these cases you don't have to assume they're getting
married when the person is still three years old. Okay, she converted
when she was three. Anyway, yeah, we rule like רבי שמעון בר
יוחאי *Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai*. אמר ליה *amar lei*, so he said
back to him, זיל אפיק *zil afik*, go and divorce her, ואי
לא מפיקנא לך רבי יעקב בר אידי מאונך *ve'i lo mapkina lach
Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi me'unach*, I'll pull רבי יעקב בר אידי *Rabbi
Yaakov bar Idi* out of your ear. Don't tell me oh, רבי
יעקב בר אידי *Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi* says we rule like רבי
שמעון בר יוחאי *Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai*, you know, you and רבי
יעקב בר אידי *Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi* goodbye, you know, whatever. Forget
about that. We do not פסקן *pasken* that way and I'm going
to force you to divorce her. Okay, so here's a very different
ruling. תניא וכן רבי שמעון בן יוחי אומר *tanya vechein Rabbi Shimon
ben Yochai omer*. Okay, so that's the end. We don't know the
conclusion. Although since the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* ends with a מעשה ma'aseh
רב *maaseh rav*, an actual story, although there was another מעשה רב
*maaseh rav* before about רבי *Rabbi*, but you know, sort of it
ends with the line like you know, I'll pull רבי יעקב בר
אידי *Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi* out of your ear, like to heck
with רבי יעקב בר אידי *Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi*, we don't rule
that way, you know, that leads a lot of פוסקים *poskim* to
assume we don't rule that way, and even פחות מבת שלש שנים
*pachos mibat shalosh shanim* is אסור *assur* to a כהן Kohen, *Kohen*.
We had it before, you know that he couldn't marry until עד
שיאמו מישראל *ad sheyeamu miYisrael*, way back on נ"ז *nun-zayin*, wasn't it?
We had that? Yeah, but we didn't rule that way either. But
here there's a... anyway, I don't want to... yes, you're correct, but
let's not worry right now about reconciling. Okay. But anyway here there's
a debate of ראשונים *Rishonim* how do we rule about גיורת פחות
מבת שלש שנים *giyoret pachos mibat shalosh shanim*. What do we say?
I'm not getting into all that right now. Okay. But there is
a debate of ראשונים *Rishonim* how we rule about that. Okay. תניא
וכן רבי שמעון בן יוחי אומר *tanya vechein Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai
omer*, now since we're talking about interesting rulings of רבי שמעון בר
יוחאי *Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai* about non-Jews, so the current ruling we
just gave was a more sympathetic one, you might say. I mean,
okay, he didn't say that any convert is okay, but at least
פחות מג' שנים *pachos migimel shanim*. Now let's take a look at
a ruling of his that could be made a more Jew-non-Jew distinction
in a way that has been—is famously something that people have been
like challenged. So וכן רבי שמעון בן יוחי אומר קברי עובדי כוכבים
אינם מטמאים באהל *vechein Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai omer kivrei ovdei kochavim
einam mitamim be'ohel*, the graves of non-Jews do not cause טומאה *tumah*
in an אהל *ohel*. שנאמר ואתן צאני צאן מרעיתי אדם Adam אתם
*sheneemar ve'atem tzoni tzon mariti adam atem*, as it says: and you
are my flock, the flock of my pasturing, you are אדם Adam.
*adam*. אתם קרויין אדם Adam *atem keruyin adam*, you are called אדם
Adam *adam*, you my flock, the Jewish people, ואין עובדי כוכבים קרויין
אדם Adam. *ve'ein ovdei kochavim keruyin adam*, the non-Jews are not called
אדם Adam *adam*. So it's a leniency for us, but anyway you
could understand how that could be seen as very dehumanizing of non-Jews
and it's particularly ironic when it's juxtaposed to the previous thing where
he's more willing to—I mean maybe you could say in both cases
he's being lenient. But okay, but you know there he's not being
completely dismissive. Now I'll talk about a תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* in a
minute who deals with nuancing this, but let's just finish the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. מיתיבי *Meisivei* I think on נפש אדם Adam *Nefesh Adam*
16a, so it says the people were 16,000 by the by the
again the Midian. So you see it's calling them אדם Adam *Adam*.
No, משום mishum בהמה *mishum beheima*. That's contrastive to the animals. But
it's not but it's but so in that context it has to
say אדם *Adam*. אשר יש בה הרבה משתים עשרה רבו אדם אשר
לא ידע בין ימינו לשמאלו *Asher yesh bah harbeh mishteim esreh ribo
adam asher lo yada bein yemino lismolo*. This is by Nineveh, 12,000,
no 12 myriad, 120,000 people and it calls them אדם *Adam*. So
the הגה *hagah* here took off the end of the פסוק *pasuk*
because then it becomes sort of an obvious ובהמה רבה *u'beheima rabah*
is the end of the פסוק *pasuk*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says no, משום בהמה *mishum beheima*. That was to contrast it with
the בהמה *beheima*. But that's why it used the word אדם *Adam*,
otherwise it wouldn't. רש"י *Rashi* helpfully tells us and רש"י *Rashi* says
where's the רש"י *Rashi*? The first narrow line, אנשי נינוה עובדי כוכבים
היו *Anshei Ninveh ovdei kochavim hayu*. Okay. By the way, the people
of Nineveh were non-Jews. It's like so funny that he had to
tell us that. Maybe because we read it every יום כיפור *Yom
Kippur* we think we must think that it's Jewish or something, I
don't know. Anyway, כל הורג נפש וכל נוגע בחלל תתחטאו *Kol horeig
nefesh vechol nogeia bechalal titchata'u*. It says anybody who killed somebody has
to purify themselves and there they were going at war against Midian,
so that's non-Jews. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, דילמא איקטיל
חד מישראל *dilma ikatil chad miYisrael*. That's because maybe a Jew was
killed. ורבנן *Ve'rabbanan*, so the rabbis think they killed a Jew? No,
לא נפקד ממנו איש *lo nifkad mimenu ish*. No, that didn't happen,
nobody was missing. רבי שמעון בר יוחאי *Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai*, לא
נפקד ממנו איש לעבירה *lo nifkad mimenu ish la'aveirah*, it means nobody
sinned in terms of maybe, you know, having had sex with a
Midianite woman, but maybe a Jew was actually killed. רבינא *Ravina* אמר
*amar*, now רבינא *Ravina* says, and this is the very important לכהלכה
*lehalacha*, מהיכא דמייתי מקרא נופל *me'heicha d'mayisei mikra nopal*. The last פסוק
*pasuk* is here's the real answer. Although רבי שמעון בר יוחאי *Rabbi
Shimon bar Yochai* says the פסוק *pasuk* excludes non-Jews from טומאת אוהל
tumat ohel, *tumas ohel*, from communicating טומאה *tumah* if they're under the
same roof, a non-Jewish body. But מטמא במגע ובמשא *metamei be'maga u've'massa*,
they're not excluded from contact טומאה *tumah*. Now that is very important
because because of that, if we if there was a position they
were totally excluded from contact טומאה *tumah*, the whole question of like
can a כהן Kohen. *Kohen* be a doctor would completely go away,
right? Because of the because a כהן Kohen. *Kohen*, you know, there's
one question about can a כהן Kohen *Kohen* ever go into a
hospital? Right? Because are there like, you know, there's non, there's bodies
in the morgue. But if you say non-Jews it's not a problem,
then it depends well which hospital is it, is it a Jewish
hospital or not, or whatever. But in some cases you can generally
work with an assumption that we don't, you know, we don't have
to assume that there's necessarily a Jewish body in the morgue, and,
you know, and that allows obviously for leniencies because non-Jews are not
מטמא באוהל *metamei be'ohel*. Why? How can you fly over cemeteries? You
know, now that's a question when you have Jewish cemeteries also. I
have relatives who are כהנים kohanim *Kohanim*, I mean, some they're not
whatever blood relatives, who don't go into the Metropolitan Museum because of
the mummies. So they're being חושש *choshesh* that a non-Jew is מטמא
באוהל *metamei be'ohel*. But if we were to say that a non-Jew
is not מטמא במגע *metamei be'maga*, then it would be tremendously lenient.
So it says no, מטמא במגע *metamei be'maga*. They're not מטמא *metamei*.
The issue is מטמא באוהל *metamei be'ohel*. Now there's a question about
how do we פוסקין *paskin*? Do we פוסקין *paskin* like רבי שמעון
בר יוחאי *Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai*? Right? Do you can you go
into a hospital if it's only non-Jews in the morgue? Can you
go into the Metropolitan Museum? So there's actually a מחלוקת *machlokes* about
this. Overwhelmingly the assumption is is that we do פוסקין *paskin* like
רבי שמעון בר יוחאי *Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai* and non-Jew is not
מטמא באוהל *metamei be'ohel*, but there definitely are some כהנים Kohanim *kohanim*
that are חושש *choshesh* that that even non-Jews are מטמא באוהל *metamei
be'ohel*. So if you take a look at תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos*, תוספות
*Tosafos* says, I told you what's the general acceptance that they're not.
So he says if you take a look four lines down in
the wide lines here of the תוספות *Tosafos*, ואומר ר"י *ve'omer Ri*
right under the words ממגע *mimaga*, ואומר ר"י דאין הלכה halacha, כרבי
שמעון *ve'omer Ri d'ein halacha k'Rabbi Shimon*. We don't rule like רבי
שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, דסוגיא דפליגא עליה *d'sugya d'paliga aleih* etc. So there
actually is a debate how we rule about that, but again the
consensus tends to be that they are not. Now in terms of
the issue of אדם *adam*, so תוספות *Tosafos* there's a famous contradiction
with another סוגיא *sugya* where the גמרא *Gemara* says speaks very positively
about non-Jews and says how do you know about non-Jew that that
learns תורה Torah *Torah* or that does תורה Torah, *Torah* and does
מצוות *mitzvos* that they're even as great as a כהן גדול kohen
gadol, *Kohen Gadol*? Because it says אדם *adam*... what's the of course
what's the exact פסוק *pasuk*? What? אשר יעשה אותם האדם וחי בהם
*Asher ya'aseh osam ha'adam vachai bahem*. כהנים Kohanim. לויים ישראלים *Kohanim, Leviyim,
Yisraelim* לא נאמר אלא האדם *lo ne'emar ela ha'adam*. Even a non-Jew.
So how do you deal with it? So רש"י *Rashi* says okay
it's מחלוקת *machlokes*. רבי שמעון בר יוחאי *Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai* thinks
אדם *adam* excludes non-Jews, right? And another תנא *tana* thinks אדם *adam*
includes non-Jews. Which we'd have רבי שמעון בר יוחאי *Rabbi Shimon bar
Yochai* having a very type of categorical approach towards non-Jews. תוספות *Tosafos*
tries to nuance it more. And תוספות *Tosafos* makes either there's a
difference between אדם *adam* and האדם *ha'adam*, so in some way in
sometimes if it's phrased this way it means to exclude non-Jews if
it's phrased that way it doesn't mean to exclude non-Jews. However it
works out, the good thing about that is that it doesn't make
רבי שמעון בר יוחאי *Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai* so categorical, it makes
it more like of a technical deal and not some. sweeping statement
that non-Jews can't be called, like, אדם. Give them עמדו לכם פה
עם החמור, amdu lachem po im hachamor, עם הדומה לחמור. am hadomeh
l'chamor. I know, I know. I understand why there's a reason to
think that תוספות is not necessarily פשט. pshat. Yes, Charlie. I know
a Cohen who went to medical school based on the idea that
non-Jews don't cause טומאת אוהל, ohel, but
he was also instructed not to dissect a cadaver. Right. Right. So
that's the thing. It's one thing being under the same, but having...
how do you get away with not dissecting a cadaver? I thought
you can't touch... He had his roommate from Yeshiva College be his
partner and did... That was okay? You could get a medical degree
without ever having actually... He's practicing medicine today. Okay, fine. I do
want to show you... right. You know what they say? What do
you call the person who graduated last in his class in medical
school? Doctor. Okay, so anyway... so that's the only reason why your
relatives won't go into the... anyway, so, shh, I want to read
you a different answer that's normally not known about this in תוספות.
About ten lines before the lines get wide, the line starts ודכתיב,
v'dichtiv, he says, והרב משולם היה אומר, v'Harav Meshullam haya omer, דגבי
פורענות, d'gabei puranut, דווקא, davka, all the פסוקים psukim he quoted here
were about killing people, or people dying, right? And there it said
אדם versus non-Jew. דגבי פורענות, d'gabei puranut, דווקא קאמר אתם קרויים אדם,
davka ka'amar atem kruyim Adam, דלא ליכתוב ישראל בהדיא גבי פורענות. d'lo
lichtov Yisrael b'hedya gabei puranut. Okay? That it didn't want to speak
say explicitly like it says if a ישראל Yisrael dies in an
אוהל, ישראל כי ימות באוהל. Yisrael ki yamut b'ohel. So it says
אדם. Okay? And that's why it said אדם there because it didn't
want to say ישראל, Yisrael, אדם there means ישראל. Yisrael. אבל גבי
האדם וחי, aval gabei ha'adam v'chai, אמרינן בהדיא קרויים ישראל אדם, amrinan
b'hedya kruyim Yisrael Adam, כמו רגיל בכל מקום. k'mo ragil b'chol makom.
So he says, so he says, it's not because we think non-Jews
are not אדם. It says in a context where we can understand
the פסוקים don't want to explicitly say ישראל Yisrael because it talks
about dying, we'll say the word אדם is used as a way
of saying ישראל. Yisrael. But as a general rule, אדם means everybody.
אדם means Jews and non-Jews. Nice. Very nice. People don't normally know
that answer. Okay. So, moving on. But now we still have this
big question about the status of a יבמה, yevama, which is going
to continue. Let's keep on going. אירס את האלמנה, iras et ha'almana,
ונתמנה להיות כהן גדול, v'nitmana l'hiyot kohen gadol, we had this before,
quoted earlier, somebody did קידושין kiddushin with an אלמנה, almana, no problem
for a normal כהן, Kohen and then he became a כהן גדול.
Kohen Gadol. יכנוס, yichnos, he can go ahead and do the נישואין.
nisuin. And we discussed before how much does that indicate that the
הלכות halachot of a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, apply only in terms
of קידושין kiddushin or not נישואין, nisuin, or how much is it
because here he sort of gets grandfathered in since he was already
sort of married to her in this state. Okay. ומעשה ביהושע בן
גמלא, umas'eh b'Yehoshua ben Gamla, there's a story of Yehoshua ben Gamla,
שקידש את מרתא בת בייתוס, shekidesh et Marta bat Baitos, he married
this woman, Marta bat Baitos, ומינהו המלך להיות כהן גדול, uminahu hamelech
l'hiyot kohen gadol, and then the king appointed him to be a
כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol וכינסה, v'chinasa, and then he married, and then
he did נישואין. nisuin. So there you go. We had a מעשה
that actually it was acted on like this. Okay. So even though
the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol he did נישואין nisuin with an אלמנה,
almana, the קידושין kiddushin, that happened before. שומרת יבם, shomeret yavam, שנפלה
לפני כהן הדיוט, shenafela lifnei kohen hedyot, if a woman is a
שומרת יבם, shomeret yavam, so she's an אלמנה, almana, okay, but this
כהן Kohen is not yet an ארוס arus to her, he hasn't
yet done אירוסין, eirusin, right, it's just a שומרת יבם, shomeret yavam,
ונתמנה להיות כהן גדול, v'nitmana l'hiyot kohen gadol, and then he becomes
a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol. אף על פי שעשה בה מאמר, af
al pi she'asa bah ma'amar, he did an act of קידושין, kiddushin
but remember it's only rabbinic קידושין kiddushin because it's a case of
שומרת יבם. shomeret yavam. Remember יבמות? Yevamot? We were... this was מסכתא...
masechta... okay, we stayed somewhere else for a while. Anyway, in this
case, since it's not halakhically קידושין kiddushin yet and it's only זיקה
zika and מאמר, ma'amar, so since he wasn't married to... since there
was no קידושין kiddushin yet, הרי זה לא יכנוס. harei zeh lo
yichnos. He cannot go ahead. And בית שמאי Beit Shammai might disagree.
But here he cannot go ahead and do ייבום yibbum because he's
not... the קידושין kiddushin had not yet taken place. Okay. תנו רבנן,
tanu rabanan, we taught, מניין שאם אירס את האלמנה ונתמנה להיות כהן
גדול שיכנוס, minayin she'im iras et ha'almana v'nitmana l'hiyot kohen gadol sheyichnos,
תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, יקח אשה, yikach isha, אשה, take her as
an אשה. ובתולה מעמיו יקח אשה, uv'tula me'amav yikach isha, and the
way this is being read is is that יקח yikach here corresponds
to יקח yikach means קידושין kiddushin or נישואין, nisuin, here it's being
read as נישואין. nisuin. He can do נישואין nisuin with her once
she is, right, you know, even if she's already... one minute, what's
the דרשה? drasha? Right. Once she's already his wife, once she's already
his אשה, his wife, then he can go ahead and do the
נישואין nisuin with her. So the גמרא says, אי הכי שומרת יבם
נמי? ee hachi shomeret yavam nami? So just go ahead and do
it even with a שומרת יבם. shomeret yavam. No. אשה ולא יבמה.
isha v'lo yevama. No, if she's already his wife he can do
נישואין nisuin with her, but if she's just the sister-in-law he can't
go ahead and do נישואין nisuin with her. Okay. מעשה ביהושע, ma'aseh
b'Yehoshua, now the story with Yehoshua. So the גמרא points out a
difference between the language in the beginning of the משנה mishna and
the end. The beginning of the משנה mishna when the case of
Yehoshua ben Gamla says ומינהו המלך, uminahu hamelech, the king appointed him.
At the end it speaks in the case of שומרת יבם, shomeret
yavam, it says what happens if there was a זיקה zika and...
נתמנה, nitmane, he was elected, right? So there's a difference of a
passive voice and the active voice. So the גמרא says מינוהו אין,
mineihu in, by יהושע בן גמלא Yehoshua ben Gamla it says he
was appointed by the king. נתמנה לא, nitmane lo, not that he
was elected. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, now it assumes that
the idea he was elected suggests more an idea of a consensus.
Like, he was appointed means like, you know, everybody acknowledged his appointment
and so on. And as רש"י says, maybe his fellow כהנים Kohanim
are normally involved in the process, you know, sort of like the
white smoke and the—no, that's something else. Anyway, but how—right, how—so, so,
so it's not just a one-person appointment from above. There's a whole
process and the result of the process is נתמנה. nitmane. It doesn't
say that here. It says מינוהו המלך. mineihu hamelech. So אמר רב
יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, קשר כחזינא הכא. kesher kachazina hacha. I see
a little like—I see some conspiracy going on here, like a band,
you know, like people working together. דאמר רב אסי, De'amar Rav Assi,
תרקבא דדינרי tirkava de'dinari עיילי ליה ayeili lei מרתא בת בייתוס Marta
Bas Baitos to this אלמנה almanah that he married was a very
rich אלמנה almanah and a whole like basket fill of דינרי dinarei
מרתא בת בייתוס Marta Bas Baitos sort of sent לינאי המלך le'Yannai
hamelech עד דמוקי ליה ליהושע בן גמלא בכהני רברבי ad demokei lei
le'Yehoshua ben Gamla be'kahanei ravrevei until he made יהושע בן גמלא Yehoshua
ben Gamla כהן גדול. kohen gadol So basically the king was bribed
so that her husband could become a כהן Kohen גדול, who he
conveniently had already done קידושין kiddushin but not yet נישואין nissuim with
actually נישואין nissuim would have made it even better, but anyway—and that's
why he was appointed by the king, even though it was not
something that a position he normally otherwise would have had. ישר כח.
Yasher koach. Yes, she appears in the קמצא ובר קמצא Kamtza u'Bar
Kamtza narrative, where her wealth doesn't do her any good in that.
Exactly. Okay, so now the גמרא says like this. Let me just
check what this is. Okay, the next משנה. Mishnah. כהן גדול שמת,
Kohen Gadol she'mes, if a כהן Kohen גדול dies, אחיו—I'm achiv sorry,
I read that wrong. כהן גדול שמת אחיו, Kohen Gadol she'mes achiv,
a כהן Kohen גדול whose brother dies. So now he's faced with
an אלמנה almanah as his sister-in-law, as a מצוה mitzvah of יבום.
yibum. חולץ ולא מייבם. Choletz v'lo meyavem. He does חליצה chalitzah and
not יבום. yibum. So the גמרא says פסיק ותני. passik v'sanei. You're
not making distinctions. לא שנא מן האירוסין ולא שנא מן הנישואין. Lo
shna min ha'eirusin v'lo shna min ha'nissuim. It doesn't matter if this
woman who's an אלמנה almanah that's standing in front of him is
an אלמנה almanah from אירוסין eirusin or from נישואין. nissuim. בשלמא מן
הנישואין, Bishlama min ha'nissuim, I get why he can't do יבום yibum
if he had נישואין nissuim with his brother. עשה ולא תעשה הוא.
Aseh v'lo sa'aseh hu. There's an עשה aseh of בתולה מעמו יקח
אשה. besulah me'amo yikach ishah. She's assumed to be a non-בתולה besulah
because he had נישואין. nissuim. And she's a לא תעשה lo sa'aseh
of an אלמנה. almanah. And that can't override—the מצות עשה mitzvas aseh
of יבום yibum doesn't override דחי לא תעשה ועשה. dachi lo sa'aseh
v'aseh. אלא מן האירוסין, Ella min ha'eirusin, if there was just—if she
was just married to the brother by אירוסין, eirusin, so it's only
the לא תעשה lo sa'aseh of an אלמנה. almanah. There's no מצות
עשה mitzvas aseh because she might be—very well be a virgin. So
if that's true, יבוא עשה וידחה לא תעשה. yavo aseh v'yidchei lo
sa'aseh. Let the עשה aseh of יבום yibum override the לא תעשה.
lo sa'aseh. So the גמרא says, you know what, in principle you're
right, but גזירה ביאה ראשונה אטו ביאה שנייה. gezeirah bi'ah rishonah atu
bi'ah shniyah. That only allows the first act of sex. The first
act of sex is the מצוה. mitzvah. Afterwards there's no longer a
מצות עשה. mitzvas aseh. So he would have to do the act
of יבום yibum and then divorce her. And we're not going to
let him do the act of יבום yibum because we're afraid they'll
stay married and the second act of sex will no longer be
the מצות עשה. mitzvas aseh. That's a funny thing. You could have
said that the first act of ביאה bi'ah would have then nullified
the past status of her and—No. Why? Let's say a כהן, kohen
let's say a כהן kohen like the גמרא said before, is מקדש
זונה. mekadesh zonah. You don't say, oh, well, now that they're קידושין
we ignore her הלכה status. If he marries—well, we said, we saw—oh,
you mean she wouldn't be called an אלמנה almanah because that has
to do with her marital status. Exactly. Interesting. Okay, so the גמרא
does not say that. תוספות makes another point. Let's look at תוספות.
He says, כהן גדול שמת אחיו חולץ ולא מייבם. Kohen Gadol she'mes
achiv choletz v'lo meyavem. So תוספות says, ואם תאמר רישא שמעינן לה
דקתני שאין יבם לכהן הדיוט, v'im tomar reisha sham'inan lah de'katni she'ein
yavam l'kohen hedyot, and אמר רבי דהכא חולץ אתא לאשמעינן. de'hacha choletz
ata l'ashme'inan. דסלקא דעתך משום בזיון דכהן גדול שרוקקת לפניו לא תחלוץ.
De'salka dach'tach mishum bizayon de'Kohen Gadol she'rokekes lefanav lo sachlotz. Imagine what
the process of חליצה chalitzah is. Here you're going to take this
woman and she's going to spit in the, you know, down in
front of a כהן kohen גדול. I understand. So אף על גב
דכבר תנן לעיל, af al gav de'kvar snan l'eil, etc. So the
point is, okay, but he has to undergo it or else she's
going to be, you know, completely an עגונה agunah her whole life.
So okay. Anyways, interesting that he points out that aspect of it.
Next משנה. Mishnah. כהן הדיוט לא ישא אילונית אלא אם כן יש
לו אשה ובנים. Kohen hedyot lo yisa ailonis ella im kein yesh
lo ishah u'banim. If you have a normal כהן, he can't marry
an אילונית, ailonis, a woman who is unable to have kids. It
doesn't just mean an עקרה. akarah. An אילונית ailonis is some type
of a woman who like physically about her body in some obvious
way has male characteristics. We'll see about it. Anyway, he can't marry
this woman unless because of the מצוה mitzvah of פרו ורבו. peru
u'revu. Unless everybody does—I know, the גמרא is going to say that.
Unless he has a wife and children. Now רש"י here says unless
he has children. The גרסא girsa wife and children is read wife
or children. Either he already has children, he was מקיים פרו ורבו,
mekayem peru u'revu, or he has another wife and he'll be able
to be מקיים פרו ורבו mekayem peru u'revu with his other wife.
Okay? So but the issue with him is whether he's going to
be able to be מקיים פרו ורבו. mekayem peru u'revu. And if
he's able to or already has been, not a problem. רבי יהודה
אומר אף על פי שיש לו אשה ובנים לא ישא אילונית. Rabi
Yehuda omer af al pi she'yesh lo ishah u'banim lo yisa ailonis.
The—now you see why we're talking about a כהן. The now you
see why we're talking about a כהן. Okay, because in order to
get to רבי יהודה'ס Rabbi Yehuda's position, the first position is it's
not a problem, it's not a כהן problem, it's just a פרו
ורבו pru u'rvu problem. Now רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda says it is
a כהן problem, even if he's been מקיים פרו ורבו, mekayeim pru
u'rvu, לא ישא אילונית שהיא זונה האמורה בתורה. lo yisa ilanit she'hi
zonah hamurah b'Torah. Now why would you say she's a זונה? zonah
Because this is a woman who can fundamentally never be in the
פרשה parsha of childbirth. And this takes an approach that sex is
only considered to be not just an act of pleasure-seeking and fornication
only because of the context of the possibility of procreation. And therefore
with this woman where it's never part of that, I mean obviously
it doesn't mean that in the case of a marriage if a
woman is post-menopausal or pregnant or other things, but there is a
procreative context that frames the sexual relationship or seen as framing it.
And he says when that's not fundamentally excluded then it's a זונה.
zonah. Now it should be noted that this is a major question
in different attitudes in the גמרא which have serious implications להלכה l'halacha
and one of them is here, whether to see marital sex this
way. If marital sex seen as being legitimate only because of the
procreative context or is it fundamentally seen as legitimate as an intrinsic
value as an intrinsic thing of והיו לבשר אחד, v'hayu l'vasar echad,
bringing husband and wife together as one. I often like to point
to the two interpretations of רש״י Rashi and the רמב״ן Ramban on
the פסוק of והיו לבשר אחד. v'hayu l'vasar echad. So רש״י Rashi
says what's והיו לבשר אחד? v'hayu l'vasar echad? Because they have a
child and through the child their flesh becomes one. Okay, which basically
says that that whole פסוק is saying why do the beautiful man
and woman come together? Because they'll have children. As opposed to the
way the רמב״ן Ramban reads it which is no, because they actually
become one as a couple. So this is reading that it should
not be understood to be the normative understanding of not just of
the definition of זונה zonah but the normative understanding of marital sex,
but that is the position here of רבי יהודה, Reb Yehuda, and
therefore he says that this would be the case of the זונה
zonah in the תורה when this is completely this type of a
woman is completely out of the procreative context. וחכמים אומרים אין זונה
אלא גיורת ומשוחררת ושנבעלה בעילת זנות. V'Chachamim omrim: Ein zonah ela giyoret
u'meshuchreret v'sheniba l'vilat znus. So we've quoted this before. גיורת, משוחררת, meshuchreret,
either because we suspect that they've had sex with a non-Jew or
the idea that I suggested maybe there's a general way of looking
at non-Jews and that's a type of an idea of זונה. Or
a Jewish woman who has had a forbidden act of sex, which
basically means two types of forbidden acts of sex. One is an
איסור כרת issur kares forbidden act of sex and the other would
be a type of act of sex that is forbidden specifically to
כהנים Kohanim. like a גרושה gerusha with a כהן and so on
although that also might make her a חללה. challalah. Okay, so those
are very important questions about the definition of a זונה for כהנים.
Let's take a look. Do you have a question before Phil? No.
Okay, so let's take a look. אמר ליה ריש גלותא לרב הונא:
Amar lei Reish Galusa l'Rav Huna: מאי טעמא? Mai taama? What's the
reason? It's in the middle of standard learning תורה, and he says
what's the reason of this משנה, mishna, the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma,
משום that he can't that a כהן can't marry an אילונית ilanit
unless he's had kids? משום פרו ורבו. Mishum pru u'rvu. So he
said אפרו ורבו כהני הוא דמיפקדי ישראל לא מיפקדי? A-pru u'rvu Kohani
hu de-miphkdi Yisrael lo miphkdi? So why do you have to tell
me that a כהן can't marry an אילונית ilanit unless he's been
מקיים פרו ורבו? mekayeim pru u'rvu? What, are only כהנים commanded on
פרו ורבו? pru u'rvu? So he says אמר ליה משום דקבעי למתנא
סיפא. Amar lei mishum de-kaba'ei l'mitna seifa. No, the whole point of
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma was a lead-in to רבי יהודה Reb
Yehuda that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma said the only problem with
a כהן is the normal problem of פרו ורבו. pru u'rvu. But
that's to get you to the סיפא seifa that רבי יהודה אומר
אף על פי שיש לו אשה ובנים, Reb Yehuda omer af al
pi she'yesh lo isha u'vanim, even forgetting פרו ורבו, pru u'rvu, there's
a problem according to רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda about an אילונית ilanit
because ויש לו בנים לא ישא אילונית שהיא זונה האמורה בתורה. v'yesh
lo banim lo yisa ilanit she'hi zonah hamurah b'Torah. Not getting any
questions right now. Okay, now אזונה כהני הוא דמיפקדי וישראל לא מיפקדי?
A-zonah Kohani hu de-miphkdi v'Yisrael lo miphkdi? So it's to get you
to רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda that says that no, even with kids
it's a זונה problem, and that is why it's specifically a problem
for כהנים. Okay, משום הכי תני כהנים. Mishum achei tanei Kohanim. אמר
רב הונא מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה? Amar Rav Huna: Mai taama de-Reb
Yehuda? What's the reason of רבי יהודה? Reb Yehuda? דכתיב אכלו ולא
ישבעו הזנו ולא יפרצו. Dichsiv achlu v'lo yisbau hiznu v'lo yifrotzu. They
will eat and not be satisfied, they will fornicate and will not
somehow burst forth. So what does that mean? כל ביאה שאין בה
פרצה Kol biah she-ein bah pirtzah or פרצה, pertzah, any sex that
does not have the idea of ופרצת ימה וקדמה u'faratzta yama va-keidma
etc., that does not have the idea of spreading forth your progeny,
is not an appropriate context, אינה אלא בעילת זנות, eina ela bilat
znus, is fundamentally just an act of fornication. It has to be
in a type of a procreative context. תוספות says right at the
top here כל ביאה שאין בה פרצה קטנה אף על פי דכלולה
בפרצה לכשתתגדר. kol biah she-ein bah pertzah ktana af al pi d'klal
pertzah l'chshe-tisgader. Okay, ולא ממעט, v'lo memait, so קטנה ktana and other
types of cases eventually it's in that context, it's the broader context,
but it was in it whatever, it's an interesting question. I mean
let's say they got married after menopause, but somehow in terms of
the people involved it's not like it was fundamentally categorically off the
table. I would say that this attitude that sex is only legitimated
because of the procreative element, you find echoes to it even in
more strict ways than this. I mean... Again, not as strict הלכה,
but still as attitudinal issues, like in the רמב״ם Rambam and elsewhere
you get this idea that when he discusses the problem of זרע
לבטלה, zera levatala, you get the idea that it sounds a little
bit like for a man having sex with his wife when she’s
not fertile is a quasi זרע לבטלה zera levatala problem. Never black
and white says it, but this type of idea is sort of
present even beyond these contexts and he’s saying that very much about
sex being legitimated because of the procreative aspect. Let’s just read, I
know we have one minute left, but I just want to read
the next piece, it’s the קטנה ktana. at the end of this
thought. תניא, we learned in a ברייתא, braita, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi
Eliezer omer, כהן לא ישא את הקטנה, kohen lo yissa et haktana,
a כהן can’t marry a קטנה. ktana That’s so funny because before
we spoke about a כהן גדול דווקא davka marrying maybe a קטנה
ktana or so רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, okay, so אמר ליה רב
חסדא לרבה, amar lei Rav Chisda leRabba, פוק עיין בה, puk iyein
bah, go look into this what this position is based on, דלאורתא
בעי ליה רב הונא מינך d’le’orta bei lei Rav Huna minech because
tonight רב הונא’s going to ask you what’s behind רבי אליעזר’s Rabbi
Eliezer position. And now we’re going to go on to find a
reason, I’ll give you, we’ll read the first reason, we’ll unpack it
tomorrow. נפק עיין בה, nafak iyein bah, he went and looked into
it and this is the conclusion he came to, why a קטנה
ktana. is a problem. רבי אליעזר סבר לה כרבי מאיר וסבר לה
כרבי יהודה. Rabbi Eliezer savar lah keRabbi Meir vesavar lah keRabbi Yehuda.
It’s a combination of two positions, רבי מאיר’s Rabbi Meir position and
a רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda position. סבר לה כרבי מאיר דחייש למיעוטא.
savar lah keRabbi Meir dechayeish lemiyuta. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir in general
is concerned for even small possibilities. וסבר לה כרבי יהודה דאמר איילונית
זונה היא. vesavar lah keRabbi Yehuda de’amar ailonit zona hi. A, he’s
concerned that if a woman’s an איילונית ailonit she’s אסור to a
כהן and he’s concerned that even for small percentage possibilities. So never
marry a קטנה. ktana? Why should a כהן never marry a קטנה?
ktana Because maybe in 2% of the cases she’ll turn out to
be an איילונית ailonit and that’s the reason. Now the גמרא’s going
to go ahead and unpack that and we’ll do that tomorrow. But
what I wanted to say is what could he have said? He
could have said don’t marry a קטנה ktana because it’s ביאת זנות,
biat znut, right? Because it’s not procreative. So that’s why it does.
Even when we’re saying that that איילונית ailonit is considered ביאת זנות,
biat znut, it has to be procreative, we don’t mean looking at
every single act. We mean a much a bigger picture. So if
a woman’s a קטנה ktana, or she’s post-menopause or she’s pregnant, nobody’s
calling that ביאת זנות, biat znut, okay? What we’re calling ביאת זנות
biat znut is when there’s a sense of categorical exclusion. Alright. Now
of course one has to think about this poor woman who probably
the only thing she wants to do in her, I don’t know,
it’s not to say that. Anyways basically it feels like she can’t
have kids and we’re basically now saying and anytime you have sex
we’re going to consider it a type of a ביאת זנות. biat
znut. But so that’s obviously an issue that also has to be
pointed out here. But anyway the point is it’s a fundamental attitude
of how to look at sex that it’s only legitimated in the
procreative context, but even within that, not saying it at every single
act. קטנה, ktana the גמרא דווקא Gemara davka does not suggest by
קטנה ktana, that the problem is ביאת זנות. biat znut. It looks
for other reasons. Now we would have other issues with קטנה, ktana.
not ביאת זנות, biat znut, child abuse and so on. But in
terms of the attitudes towards sex, the גמרא does not suggest that’s
what’s going on by קטנה. So tomorrow we’ll see how the גמרא
deals with these explanations tomorrow. So we don’t see the other way
around, let him marry an איילונית ailonit and then later on marry
a wife who’s become...